{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man was forced to recognize Alexander III as pope after signing the Peace of Venice. In one battle, the “Company of Death” successfully defended Aribert’s carroccio from this man. This man’s attempt to control the papacy was thwarted at Legnano by the Lombard League. In another campaign, this man drowned in the Saleph River before he could join the forces of Philip Augustus and Richard I. Named for his red beard, for ten points, identify this Holy Roman Emperor who died on the Third Crusade.",
      "answer": [
        "Frederick I",
        "Frederick Barbarossa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One character in this work becomes pregnant after a head in a calabash tree spits in her hand. This work begins with a creation story where wooden people are killed in a flood. In this work, one character has his head stolen by Camazotz when he’s decapitated in the House of the Bats, which he visits after the House of Dark and the House of Cold. The Hero Twins become the sun and moon after defeating the lords of Xibalba by winning the ball game in, for ten points, what Mayan collection of myths?",
      "answer": "The Popol Vuh"
    },
    {
      "question": "The earlier iterations of this publication offered advice from “Father Abraham”, many of whose sayings were collected in The Way to Wealth. This publication predicted the death of Titan Leeds and, when Leeds did not die on the predicted date, claimed that he had been replaced by an impostor. The creator of this publication was inspired by Rider’s British Merlin to the degree that he stole its authors name, Richard Saunders, as his pseudonym. For ten points, name this publication by Benjamin Franklin which offered witty sayings as well as seasonal weather information.",
      "answer": "Poor Richard’s Almanac"
    },
    {
      "question": "The SB attempted to humiliate this man in the “Trianglo” action. Juan Maria Fernandez Krohn attempted to stab this man with a bayonet during his visit to Fatima. Another assassination attempt on this man was carried out by Grey Wolf member Mehmet Ali Agca. This man promulgated the Pastor bonus and the Catechism of the Catholic Church. A 1979 visit by this man to Warsaw helped inspire the creation of Solidarity. For ten points, name this predecessor of Benedict XVI, a Polish-born Pope.",
      "answer": [
        "John Paul II",
        "Karol Jozef Wojtyla"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One leader of this country declared that “the revolution has no winners and no losers” and used the policy of Chehabism. Bashir Gemayel led the left wing Kataeb Phalange Party in this country, where a 1958 crisis prompted Dwight Eisenhower to authorize a U.S. intervention for Camille Chamoun in Operation Blue Bat. This country’s 1943 National Pact shares power between Sunni and Shia Muslims, Greek Orthodox and Maronite Christians, and Druze in, for ten points, what country centered at Beirut?",
      "answer": "Lebanon"
    },
    {
      "question": "Canadian aboriginal William Arnold Combes accused this person of kidnapping ten indigenous children. In 2017, the Paradise Papers revealed that this person’s Duchy of Lancaster held offshore accounts to avoid paying taxes. This woman was criticized for not flying a flag at half-mast after the death of her daughter-in-law Princess Diana. For ten points, name this queen who succeeded her father George VI as the monarch of the United Kingdom.",
      "answer": "Elizabeth II"
    },
    {
      "question": "James Knight captured Fort Albany for this company while in 1686, Pierre le Moyne d’Iberville captured this company’s post of Moose Factory. As Chief Factor in this company’s Columbia District, John McLoughlin became known as “father of Oregon”. Indigo stripes called points were put on blankets that this company exchanged. The North West company encroached on this corporation, which was granted Prince Rupert’s Land. Often employing First Nation trappers, for ten points, name this company named for a bay in Canada.",
      "answer": "Hudson’s Bay Company"
    },
    {
      "question": "A general of this dynasty wrote the lyrical poem Man Jiang Hong. That general serving this dynasty had four words tattooed onto his back and was named Yue Fei. This dynasty was the first to establish a permanent navy, although its last emperor drowned at the Battle of Yamen. The Jingkang Incident began the Southern period of this dynasty, which lost its capital Kaifeng to the Jurchen-led Jin dynasty. For ten points, name this dynasty conquered by the Mongol Yuan dynasty.",
      "answer": [
        "Song Dynasty",
        "Northern Song until “Southern Period”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A chord made up of the notes F, B, D-sharp, and G-sharp is named for an operatic character of this composer. Ludwig II’s design of Neuschwanstein Castle contains many references to the works of this composer. This composer, who wrote the controversial essay “Jewishness in Music,” wrote an opera with excerpted numbers such as “Elsa’s Procession to the Cathedral” and the “Bridal Chorus.” The Bayreuth Festival honors the operas of, for ten points, what composer of the Ring Cycle?",
      "answer": "Richard Wagner"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the aftermath of this event, Edward Teller wrote that Jane Fonda suffering a heart attack was the only victim of it. John Kemeny led an investigation in this event which found that a similar occurrence at the David-Besse facility should have provided enough warning. A faulty valve created by Babcock and Wilcox was the cause of this event. During this event, a voluntary evacuation near Harrisburg was carried out after the failure of reactor 2. For ten points, name this partial nuclear meltdown that occurred on a Pennsylvania island.",
      "answer": "Three Mile Island accident"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was the site of the world’s first aerial bombardment when Giulio Gavotti dropped four grenades from his biplane. It’s not Ethiopia, but Rodolfo Graziani forced thousands of this country’s people into concentration camps. The “Lion of the Desert,” Omar Mukhtar, led the Senussids in a resistance movement centered on this country’s region of Cyrenaica. Mussolini’s idea of the “Fourth Shore” centered on, for ten points, what country that Italy invaded at Tripolitania?",
        "answer": "State of Libya"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This king of Libya and native Senussid led Libya after its independence following World War II. He was overthrown in 1969. ANSWER:IdrisofLibya(acceptElSayyidPrinceMuhammadIdrisbinMuhammadal-Mahdias-Senussi) (2) A member of this family wrote a work which criticized the “Arbitrary Government” erected “Under Sir Edmund Andros.” Zabdiel Boylston was convinced by a member of this family, who himself was inspired by his slave Onesimus, to inoculate hundreds of people against smallpox. During one event, a member of this family warned against a reliance on “spectral evidence” and later wrote to William Stoughton congratulating him for extinguishing devilism. For ten points, name this Massachusetts Puritan family which included “Increase” and “Cotton”.",
        "answer": "Mather BONUS: Increase Mather rallied against Edmund Andros’ governorship of the “Dominion” of this region. ANSWER: New England"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A Vachel Lindsay poem titles one book about this state by Adam Hothschild which criticized its titular monarch for his personal greed in exploiting this state. The Force Publique cut off hands and otherwise mutilated slaves who failed to reach their quotas of rubber and ivory in this state. King Leopold’s Ghost describes the atrocities in, for ten points, what central African colony privately owned by Leopold II of Belgium centered on what is nowadays Kinshasha?",
        "answer": [
          "Congo Free State",
          "Belgian Congo before “Belgium”"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This British diplomat authored a namesake report on the abuses in the Congo Free State, helping force Leopold to turn over the colony to the Belgian government. This man was later hanged for trying to procure German arms for the Easter Rising.",
        "answer": "Roger Casement"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While attempting to synthesize quinine by oxidizing aniline, William Henry Perkins accidentally discovered the first synthetic type of this substance, which he called mauveine. An expensive type of this substance was extracted from the Muricidae genus by leaving sea snails to decompose and was named after Tyre. One plant to make this substance was imported and named for India before it was planted in the southern US. Indigo is a type of, for ten points, what substance used to color fabrics?",
        "answer": "dyes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The dye produced in Tyre and mauveine were both this expensive color, which was associated with royalty in the Roman Empire.",
        "answer": "purple"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The basis of this initiative was laid out in a report by Lewis H. Brown which included a plan to break the “vicious coal cycle.” The formulator of this initiative claimed that the “the division of labor...is in danger of breaking down” while advocating for this plan at a Harvard commencement address. This plan replaced an earlier one devised by Henry Morgenthau which dictated that no steps be taken to rehabilitate the German economy. For ten points, name this plan, named for Harry Truman’s Secretary of State, to rebuild Europe in the aftermath of World War II.",
        "answer": [
          "Marshall plan",
          "European Recovery Program",
          "ERP"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Marshall Plan was rejected by Eastern European countries who, on the urging of Joseph Stalin, instead adopted this Soviet plan named for Stalin’s foreign minister.",
        "answer": "Molotov Plan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country’s sovereignty was threatened by the USSR during the Note Crisis. Nikita Khrushchev declared that this country’s relations with the USSR had deteriorated to a “night frost” in 1958. The Paasikvi-Kekkonen Doctrine preserved relations between this country and both NATO and the Warsaw Pact. Gerald Ford and Leonid Brezhnev signed a 1975 agreement in this country’s capital intended to ease Cold War tensions. For ten points, name this country where the Helsinki Accords were signed.",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Finland",
          "Suomen tasavalta",
          "Republiken Finland"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man led the Finnish resistance to the Soviet Union during both the Winter War and the Continuation War and served as Finland’s first postwar president.",
        "answer": "Carl Gustaf Emil Mannerheim"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Jawed Mojaddedi undertook a recent effort to translate this author into English. A translator of this author, Coleman Barks, sparked controversy for not knowing the language that this author wrote in. This author wrote “The Song of The Reed Flute” and featured a poem that ended each line with a Greek word in his collection Divan. This author wrote the 50,000 line Masnavi in his native language, Farsi. For ten points, name this Sufi poet and author of Spiritual Couplets.",
        "answer": "Jalal al-Din Muhammad Rumi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Sufi order was named after Rumi. A common name for this order comes from a dance practice members use to reach out to God.",
        "answer": [
          "Mavlevi Order",
          "Whirling Dervishes"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Ronan Tynan had a regular gig performing this song until 2009, when his anti-Semitic remarks sparked a backlash. Kate Smith’s version of this song, recorded in 1939, was taken out of rotation at Yankee Stadium in April 2019 after performances of other, racist songs by Smith came to light. The Yankees started hosting regular performances of this song during their 7th inning stretch after the 9/11 attacks, though some teams only use this song during Sunday games. For ten points, name this patriotic tune whose title is followed by the line “land that I love.”",
        "answer": "God Bless America"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "“God Bless America” was written by this American songwriter, who also wrote “White Christmas.”",
        "answer": "Irving Berlin"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Battle of Gettysburg",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "State in which the battle took place.",
          "answer": "Pennsylvania"
        },
        {
          "question": "National holiday that immediately followed the last day of fighting.",
          "answer": "Fourth of July"
        },
        {
          "question": "Supposed inventor of baseball, a Union officer who took over from the killed John Reynolds on the first day.",
          "answer": "Abner Doubleday"
        },
        {
          "question": "Union commander who replaced Joseph Hooker days before the battle.",
          "answer": "George Meade"
        },
        {
          "question": "Futile Confederate action on the last day that established the “High Water Mark of the Confederacy.”",
          "answer": "Pickett’s Charge"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name of the defensive position attacked in that futile action, at the center of the fish-hook line.",
          "answer": "Cemetery Ridge"
        },
        {
          "question": "Peak south of town on the “barb” of the fish-hook line; Richard Ewell attacked it all three days.",
          "answer": "Culp’s Hill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Union officer who lost his leg at Gettysburg, four years after he murdered the son of Francis Scott Key and was acquitted via temporary insanity.",
          "answer": "Daniel Sickles"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Troubles",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Region, a part of the United Kingdom, where it took place.",
          "answer": "Northern Ireland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Paramilitary organization that was the largest group to fight the British in the Troubles.",
          "answer": "Provisional Irish Republican Army or Provisional IRA"
        },
        {
          "question": "April 1998 agreement that ended the Troubles.",
          "answer": "Good Friday Agreement"
        },
        {
          "question": "Incident in 1972 in which British soldiers shot 28 civilians in Bogside.",
          "answer": [
            "Bloody Sunday",
            "Bogside Massacre early"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician who led Sinn Fein [shin fayn] from 1983-2018 and was targeted for assassination during the Troubles.",
          "answer": "Gerry Adams"
        },
        {
          "question": "Province that names a “Defence Association” that carried out that assassination attempt.",
          "answer": "Ulster"
        },
        {
          "question": "British overseas territory where 3 men were killed as part of Operation Flavius by the SAS.",
          "answer": "Gibraltar"
        },
        {
          "question": "British counter-insurgence unit, described as a legalized death squad, that set up a massage parlor as a front and was replaced by the SRU.",
          "answer": "Military Reaction Force or MRF"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Caribbean Islands",
      "prompt": "Name the Caribbean island that...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was home to a bobsled team that gained worldwide fame after the Calgary Olympics.",
          "answer": "Jamaica"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of the Parsley Massacre, in which people fled one of its countries for the other.",
          "answer": "Hispaniola"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was taken by the Dutch in 1636 and joins Bonaire and Curacao [kur-ah-sow] in the ABC islands.",
          "answer": "Aruba"
        },
        {
          "question": "Saw its capital city destroyed by the Soufriere Hills volcano in 1995.",
          "answer": "Montserrat"
        },
        {
          "question": "Saw both its French and Dutch sides devastated by Hurricane Irma in 2017.",
          "answer": "Saint Martin or Sint Maarten"
        },
        {
          "question": "Named a public square after its Nobel laureate poet, Derek Walcott.",
          "answer": "Saint Lucia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was home to a controversial US naval bombing range near Puerto Rico until 2003.",
          "answer": "Vieques , but phonetic pronunciations are acceptable, as usual"
        },
        {
          "question": "Seceded from St. Kitts and Nevis to become a separate crown colony in 1980.",
          "answer": "Anguilla"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Sophie Wahnich argues that 18th and 20th century political uses of this word differ in the sacrality of citizenship in a work titled In Defense of [this word]. Giovanna (20 pts)",
        "Borradori claimed that a phenomenon described by this word was a rejection of Enlightenment ideas in a work involving Ju¨rgen Habermas and Jacques Derrida. This word’s political use was popularized in a conservative backlash led by Edmund (10 pts)",
        "Burke to a period named for this word, where one participant claimed this word would be “the order of the day.” For ten points, what word names a reign during the French Revolution?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "“terror”",
        "terrorism"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While on the way to the Malakand Campaign, this man wrote of the Lauranian dictator Antonio Molara in Savrola. This man described fighting with the 21st Lancers at the Battle of Omdurman under Lord (20 pts)",
        "Kitchener in his work The River War. This man wrote about his ancestor, in Marlborough: His Life and Times and late in his life produced the four-volume (10 pts)",
        "History of the English Speaking Peoples. One of his speeches borrowed a Giuseppe Garibaldi phrase to state that “I have nothing to offer but blood, toil, tears, and sweat.” For ten points, name this British prime minister during WWII."
      ],
      "answer": "Winston Churchill"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Abb´e Marc-Antoine Laugier theorized a dwelling described by this word, which he thought was fundamental to architecture because it formed from nature. In addition to that hut, this word named a New York art museum which closed in 1976 and was founded by (20 pts)",
        "Nelson Rockefeller. This word was used to disparage works by Italian 14th century artists. Paul (10 pts)",
        "Gaugain influenced a movement named with this word with his depictions of idealized Tahitians; that movement was criticized for perpetuating colonial stereotypes. For ten points, name this word which connotes being at an early stage of development."
      ],
      "answer": "“primitive”"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Two answers required. V.K. Menon was forced to resign as Minister of Defense after a conflict between these two countries broke out. A series of outposts near the border between these two countries were built under the (20 pts)",
        "Forward Policy, despite both countries agreeing to the Five Principles of Peaceful Coexistence. One country granting asylum to the Dalai Lama after the 1959 (10 pts)",
        "Tibetan Uprising resulted in a 1962 border war between these two countries. Aksai Chin remains contentious between, for ten points, what two countries formerly led by Jawaharlal Nehru and Mao Zedong?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "People’s Republic of China and Republic of India",
        "PRC for “China”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Margaret of Savoy tried to calm demonstrators in this city but was ultimately forced out of the country. The Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Alcantara was fought outside this city, ending its country’s independent rule. While returning to this city’s Ajuda Hills, a royal carriage was fired upon during an assassination attempt on Joseph I, which resulted in the (10 pts)",
        "Tavora family’s public execution. The Marquis of Pombal oversaw this city’s reconstruction following an earthquake on All Saints Day in 1755. The mouth of the Tagus River is in, for ten points, what capital city of Portugal?"
      ],
      "answer": "Lisbon or Lisboa"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Edward Gorsuch was shot to death after citing this act in front of William Parker’s house in Christiana. After the passage of this legislation, John Whittier crusaded for the (20 pts)",
        "Habeas Corpus law during Vermont’s jury nullification controversy. This act was declared indisputable and superior to state laws in Prigg v. Pennsylvania and (10 pts)",
        "Ableman v. Both. Riots over the enforcement of this act did not prevent Anthony Burns from being returned to the South. For ten points, name this 1850 act that required Northerners to assist in the capture of escaped slaves."
      ],
      "answer": "Fugitive Slave Act of 1850"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After his dog fell in a hole, Marcel Ravidat discovered this location, which he thought was a secret passage to a local manor. Abb´e Henri Breuil sketched this location, which includes the (20 pts)",
        "Chamber of the Felines and the Hall of the Bulls. Ochre and hematite, as well as (10 pts)",
        "charcoal would have been used to decorate this location, which includes a painting called “The Crossed Bison” featuring primitive use of perspective. For ten points, name this French Upper Paleolithic site, which includes many wall drawings."
      ],
      "answer": "Lascaux cave"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s illegitimate daughter, Essie Mae Washington-Williams, revealed her identity at age 78. Trent Lott praised this man in 2002 claiming that, had we elected him, the US wouldn’t have had so many problems. During his campaign for governor, this man opposed the (20 pts)",
        "Barnwell Ring.” This man was the first Senator to win as a write-in candidate. In the 1948 election, this man led a party that commonly used the (10 pts)",
        "Confederate battle flag. The Dixiecrat Party was led by, for ten points, what long-time Senator from South Carolina who, in the face of the Civil Rights Act of 1957, delivered a 24-hour filibuster?"
      ],
      "answer": "Strom Thurmond"
    }
  ]
}